[
  {
    "question": "What was the consequence of the Permanent Settlement on\nrural society in Bengal?",
    "choices": "a) The zamindars invested capital and enterprise to improve\nagriculture along the lines of British yeoman farmers\nb) A group of rich peasants known\nas\njotedars succeeded in\nconsolidating their position in the villages\nc) The ryots prospered as\na\nresult of the fixed revenue\nimposed on them\nd) The system of Collectorate introduced\nthe Company for\nexercising supervisory control\non zamindars failed to take\noff",
    "answer": "(b)\nA\ngroup\nof\nrich\npeasants\nknown\nas\nJotedars\nsucceeded in consolidating their position in the villages", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe following\nwas/were\nassociated\nwith\nthe\nintroduction of the Ryotwari Settlement in India during British\nrule?\n1. Lord Cornwallis\n2.Alexander Read\n3.Thomas Munro\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\n(a)\n1 only\n(b)\n1 and 3 only\n(c)\n2 and 3 only\n(d)\n1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "(a)\n1 only\n(b)\n1 and 3 only\n(c)\n2 and 3 only\n(d)\n1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "(c) 2 and 3 only", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nWith reference to the history of India, consider the following\npairs:\n1.Aurang: In-charge of treasury of the State\n2. Banian: Indian agent of the East India Company\n3.Mirasidar\nDesignated revenue payer to the State\nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?\n(a)\n1 and 2 only\n(b)\n2 and 3 only\n(c)\n3\nonly\n(d)\n1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "(a)\n1 and 2 only\n(b)\n2 and 3 only\n(c)\n3\nonly\n(d)\n1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "(b) 2 and 3 only", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of the Permanent\nSettlement?\na) The Permanent Settlement vested landownership rights in\nthe Zamindar\nb) The Permanent Settlement continued to pay attention to\nthe customary occupancy rights of peasants\nc) The burden of the high revenue assessment was shifted to\nthe peasants under the Permanent Settlement\nd) The condition of the actual cultivators of the land declined\nunder Permanent Settlement",
    "choices": "a) The Permanent Settlement vested landownership rights in\nthe Zamindar\nb) The Permanent Settlement continued to pay attention to\nthe customary occupancy rights of peasants\nc) The burden of the high revenue assessment was shifted to\nthe peasants under the Permanent Settlement\nd) The condition of the actual cultivators of the land declined\nunder Permanent Settlement",
    "answer": "(b)\nThe\nPermanent\nSettlement\ncontinued\nto\npay\nattention to the customary occupancy rights of peasants", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following pairs is/are correctly matched?\n1. Permanent Settlement: Lord Cornwallis\n2. Ryotwari Settlement: Thomas Munro\n3.Mahalwari Settlement: Holt Mackenzie\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\na) 1 only\nb) 1 and 2\nc) 2 and 3 only\nd) 1,2 and 3",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\nb) 1 and 2\nc) 2 and 3 only\nd) 1,2 and 3",
    "answer": "(d) 1,2 and 3\nonly", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to Ryotwari Settlement, consider the following\nstatements\n1. The\nrent\nwas\ndirectly\nby\nthe\npeasants\nto\nthe\ngovernment:\n2. The government gave the Pattas to the Ryots.\n3.The lands were surveyed and assessed\nbefore being taxed:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n(a)\n1 only\n(b)\n1 and 2 only\n1, 2 and 3\n(d)\nNone of the above",
    "choices": "(a)\n1 only\n(b)\n1 and 2 only\n1, 2 and 3\n(d)\nNone of the above",
    "answer": "(c) 1, 2 and 3", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "The tendency for\nincreased  litigation\nwas\nvisible\nafter\nthe\nintroduction of the land settlement system of Lord Cornwallis\nin 1793. The reason for this is normally traced to which of the\nfollowing provisions?\n(a)\nMaking Zamindar's position stronger vis-a-vis the Ryot\n(b)\nMaking East India Company an overlord of Zamindars\n(c)\nMaking the judicial system more efficient\n(d)\nNone of the above",
    "choices": "(a)\nMaking Zamindar's position stronger vis-a-vis the Ryot\n(b)\nMaking East India Company an overlord of Zamindars\n(c)\nMaking the judicial system more efficient\n(d)\nNone of the above",
    "answer": "(d) None of the above", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "paid\nWhich of the following is/are characteristic(s) of the Ryotwari\nsystem?\n1.It was the brainchild of Thomas Munro\n2.It was meant to reduce intermediaries\n3.Cultivating peasants\nwere gradually impoverished by the\nsystem\n4.It was introduced in parts of Madras and Bengal Presidency\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\na) 1 only\nb)1, 2 and 3\nc) 2 and 4 only\nd)2,3 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\nb)1, 2 and 3\nc) 2 and 4 only\nd)2,3 and 4",
    "answer": "(b) 1,2 and 3", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements with regard to ryotwari\nsettlement is not correct?\na)In southern and western India, the ryotwari settlement was\nadopted:\nb)Ryotwari was in principle a direct contract between the ryot\nand the state:\nc) It means a tax contract valid for usually 30 years\nd)In principle, it strengthened the former elite, the zamindars\nand weakened the peasantry:",
    "choices": "a)In southern and western India, the ryotwari settlement was\nadopted:\nb)Ryotwari was in principle a direct contract between the ryot\nand the state:\nc) It means a tax contract valid for usually 30 years\nd)In principle, it strengthened the former elite, the zamindars\nand weakened the peasantry:",
    "answer": "(d) In principle, it strengthened the former elite, the\nzamindars and weakened the peasantry", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Ryotwari experiment in land revenue was started by\na) Henry Dundas\nb)Alexander Reed\nc) David Ricardo\nd)Mountstuart Elphinstone",
    "choices": "a) Henry Dundas\nb)Alexander Reed\nc) David Ricardo\nd)Mountstuart Elphinstone",
    "answer": "(b) Alexander Reed", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nfollowing question consists of statements: Statement I and\nStatement\nIL:\nExamine\nthese\ntwo\nstatements  carefully\nand\nselect the correct answer using the code below:\nCode:\na) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the\ncorrect explanation of Statement\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not\nthe correct explanation of Statement |\nC\nStatement\nis true, but Statement Il is false\nd)Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true.\nStatement I: The Permanent Settlement was rarely extended to\nany region beyond Bengal:\nStatement\nII:\nAfter\n1810,\nthe\nagricultural\nprices\ndeclined\naffecting adversely the income of the Bengal Zamindars.",
    "choices": "a) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the\ncorrect explanation of Statement\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not\nthe correct explanation of Statement |\nC\nStatement\nis true, but Statement Il is false\nd)Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true.",
    "answer": "(c) Statement | is true, but Statement Il is false", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "The\nPermanent\nSettlement\nwas\nrarely\nextended\nto\nother\nregions because\na)An increase in agricultural prices after 1810 increased the\nvalue\nof\nthe\nharvest,\nwhile\nthe\nPermanent\nSettlement\ndisallowed an increase in the State's share\nb)the\neconomic theories\nof\nRicardo\ninfluenced\nthe policy\nmakers\nc) The state found it expedient to settle directly with the ryot\nd)all of the above",
    "choices": "a)An increase in agricultural prices after 1810 increased the\nvalue\nof\nthe\nharvest,\nwhile\nthe\nPermanent\nSettlement\ndisallowed an increase in the State's share\nb)the\neconomic theories\nof\nRicardo\ninfluenced\nthe policy\nmakers\nc) The state found it expedient to settle directly with the ryot\nd)all of the above",
    "answer": "(d) all of the above", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe\nfollowing\nintroduced\nthe\nPermanent\nSettlement of Bengal in 1793?\na) Lord Cornwallis\nb) Lord Ripon\nc) Robert Clive\nd)John Adam",
    "choices": "a) Lord Cornwallis\nb) Lord Ripon\nc) Robert Clive\nd)John Adam",
    "answer": "(a) Lord Cornwallis", 
 "topic": "Land Revenue Policies of the British"
  }
]